(
"ai_sub_version": "1.9.2",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 2,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": false,
"scrub": true
)
ウクレレ始めて1ヶ月ちょっと…
3D ウクレレ発表会っ！
It's been a little over a month since I started
the ukulele... 3D Ukulele Recital!
あったかいなー。すごい。あ、みなさん！
It's so warm... Amazing. Oh, everyone!
お待たせしてます。こんばんみぉー！
Thank you for waiting. Konbamio!
えー、大神ミオのウクレレライブへようこそいらっしゃいました。
Welcome to Ookami Mio's Ukulele Live.
本日はですね、運営さんが気を利かせてですね、
Today, the management was kind enough to...
ロケーションをこのように、ちょっと森っぽいロケーションでね、していただきましてありがとうございます。
...set up this forest-like location for me.
Thank you very much.
今日はこのミオファの森に囲まれながら、ウクレレを披露したいなって思ってます。
Today, I'd like to perform the ukulele while
surrounded by the Mio-fam forest.
こんばんみぉー！
Konbamio!
ごめんね遅れちゃって30分。
I'm sorry I'm 30 minutes late.
ちょっと前のお仕事が押してしまったんだよ。
My previous work ran over time.
で、こんなね、ちょっと焚き火をあの、くべてくれてね。
And they even set up a campfire like this for me.
ちょっと寒いから焚き火の前がいいんじゃないかということで、焚き火の前でね。
Since it's a bit cold, they thought it would be
better in front of the fire.
今日はなんかこう、ちょっとキャンプをしながらウクレレを聴いてるような、
Today, I want to perform with the feeling of...
そういう気持ちでやっていきたいと思います。
...listening to the ukulele while camping.
あ、森は燃えてないでしょ？ 大丈夫です。
Ah, the forest isn't on fire, right? It's okay.
これはね、キャンプファイヤーでやってますからね。
This is being done as a campfire.
安全を確認した上でやってますので大丈夫ですよ。
I've checked for safety, so everything is fine.
はい、ありがとう。みんな来てくれてありがとう！
Yes, thank you. Thanks for coming, everyone!
というわけでね、今日はなんと、こんなじゃじゃーん！
And so, today, look! Ta-da!
ちゃんとウクレレも召喚してもらってね、これでやっていきたいと思うんだけれども。
I've had the ukulele summoned, and I'll be
playing with this.
ちょっとね、うちは練習がてらね、チューニングはやってしまってあるので、
Since I've already finished tuning
while practicing...
今日はチューニングは省きたいと思います。みんな大好きなチューニングは。
...I'll skip the tuning today.
Even though everyone loves it.
というわけで、早速ウクレレライブ始めようと思うんだけども。
So, I'll start the ukulele live right away.
ま、まずはね、あ、最終的にウクレレ燃やすとかはない…
Well, first... Oh, I won't burn
the ukulele at the end...
あ！ ウクレレの… ウクレレがたまにウクレレなくなるんだけど、
Ah! The ukulele... It disappears occasionally, but...
そういう、あの、ものだと思ってください。はい。
...please just think of it as part of the deal. Yes.
というわけで、えーと、ウクレレライブ、まずは一番最初に弾いた、
And so, for the ukulele live, I'll start with the
first song I played...
「さんぽ」をやってみて…
..."Sanpo" (A Stroll)...
ま、それでね、あの、試験官のみんなにね、
...and I hope all you examiners out there...
「お、成長したな」って思われたいなって思っておりますので。
...will think, "Oh, she's improved."
あ、ウクレレたまに消えますが、みなさん気にせずに演奏を聴いていただければと思います。
Ah, the ukulele might disappear sometimes, but please
just ignore it and enjoy the performance.
ま、ちょっとね、森の中で聴いてるみたいなね。
It'll be like listening to it in the
middle of a forest.
ハイ。
Hi.
これがな、ちょっと、ちょっとあれだけど、ちょっと、ちょっと、こう、こう、こう...
This is, a bit, a bit like that, but a bit, a bit, like this, like this, like this...
どうしてもちょっと、ああなっちゃう。あ、これが、ちょーいい、ちょうどいい。はい。
It inevitably ends up like that. Oh, this is very good, just right. Yes.
それでは聞いてください。
Then, please listen.
ウクレレライブ、一曲目は課題曲一曲目でした。
Ukulele live, the first song was the first assigned piece.
「さんぽ」です。いきます。
It's "Sanpo". Here I go.
あるこう　あるこう
Let's walk, let's walk
私は元気
I am fine
歩くの　大好き
I love to walk
どんどん　行こう
Let's keep going
坂道
The hill road
トンネル
The tunnel
草っぱら
The grassy field
一本橋に
On the log bridge
でこぼこじゃり道
The bumpy gravel road
くものす　くぐって
Going under the spider web
下り道
The downhill road
あるこう　あるこう
Let's walk, let's walk
私は元気
I am fine
歩くの　大好き
I love to walk
間違えた！
I made a mistake!
歩くの　大好き
I love to walk
どんどん　行こう
Let's keep going
み、みつば、み、みつ、みつ、あれ？あ、こっちか。
Mi, mitsuba, mi, mitsu, mitsu, huh? Ah, this way.
みつばち　ぶんぶん
Honeybees, buzz-buzz
花畑
The flower field
日向にトカゲ
A lizard in the sun
蛇はひ…ひる…ね…
The snake is taking... a... nap...
バッタが飛んで
The grasshopper jumps
曲がり道
The winding road
イェーイ！
Yay!
「さんぽ」でした！
That was "Sanpo"!
ちょっと間違えちゃった。
I made a little mistake.
ちょっといつもと違う環境でウクレレを弾くのは少し緊張しますね。
Playing the ukulele in a slightly different environment than usual makes me a bit nervous.
ありがとうございます、試験官の皆さん。
Thank you, everyone in the jury.
そして、えーっと。
And, uh...
やはりね、こないだ、あの、先週さ、覚えてる？
As expected, recently, um, last week, do you remember?
「白日」をさ、課題曲にしたじゃん。
We made "Hakujitsu" an assigned song, didn't we?
それも弾いて、うちはみんなに、あの、合格をもらわなきゃなって思ってるのよ。
I'm thinking I have to play that too and get a passing grade from everyone.
だからみんなに、あの、「白日」を聞いてもらおうかなって思います、二曲目は。
So I think I'll have everyone listen to "Hakujitsu" for the second song.
というわけで、試験官のみんな！
So, everyone in the jury!
出番ですよ、皆さん。
It's your turn, everyone.
うちのこの３Dの体で「白日」弾きますからね。
I'm going to play "Hakujitsu" with this 3D body of mine.
じゃ、ちょっと楽譜用意しますのでお待ちくださいね。
Well, I'll prepare the sheet music, so please wait a moment.
はいしょ。
Alright.
はい、試験官の皆さん、準備はいいですか？
Okay, everyone in the jury, are you ready?
「白日」はちょっとね、難しいんですけど、練習しましたので、聴いてもらいたいと思います。
"Hakujitsu" is a bit difficult, but I've practiced it, so I'd like you to listen.
それでは。
Well then.
ちょっと間違えたら二回目、弾いてもいい？って言うかもしれない。はい。
If I make a mistake, I might say, "Can I play it a second time?" Yes.
あ、ウクレレがたまに消える。はい、それではいきます。
Ah, the ukulele disappears sometimes. Okay, here I go.
「白日」。
"Hakujitsu".
時には　誰かを
Sometimes, someone...
知らず知らずのうちに傷つけてしまったり
I end up hurting without realizing...
失ったりして初めて犯した罪を
Or losing someone, only then I realize the sins...
知る
I've committed
戻れないよ
I can't go back
昔のようには
Like the old days
煌めいて見えたとしても
Even if it looked sparkling
明日へと歩き出さなきゃ　雪が降り頻ろうとも
I must start walking towards tomorrow, even if the snow falls hard
今の僕には何ができるの　何になれるの
What can I do now? What can I become?
#大神ミオウクレレライブ
#OokamiMioUkuleleLive
白日
Hakujitsu
...誰かのために
...for someone else's sake,
生きるなら 正しいことばかり言ってらんないよな
if I'm to live, I can't just say the right things.
どこかの街でまた出会えたら
If we meet again in some town,
僕の名前を覚えていますか？
will you remember my name?
その頃にはきっと
By that time, surely,
春風が吹くだろう
the spring breeze will be blowing.
おー（ロングトーン）
Ohhh...
真っ新に生まれ変わって 人生一から始めようが
Even if I'm reborn anew and start life from scratch,
へばりついて離れない 地続きの今を歩いてるんだ
I'm walking through the continuous 'now' that's stuck and won't leave.
真っ白に全てさよなら 降りしきる雪よ
Goodbye to everything in pure white, oh falling snow,
全てを包み込んでくれ
please envelope everything.
今日だけは全てを隠してくれ
For today at least, hide everything away.
ちょ、ちょっ、ちょっと待って。みんな、ちょっと待って。
Wai- wait, wait a second. Everyone, wait just a moment.
もう一回、もう一回チャンスください。
One more time, please give me one more chance.
お願いします、もう一回チャンスください。
Please, give me one more chance.
試験官のみなさん、お願いします。
The judges, I beg you.
すみません、あの… ちょっとポジションがな。
Sorry, um... my positioning is just...
慣れない場所で弾くからポジションがうまく行かなかったな。
The positioning wasn't right since I'm in an unfamiliar place.
いいですか？すみません、あの… ありがとうございます。
Is it okay? Sorry, um... thank you very much.
ちょっと水飲む。
I'm gonna drink some water.
え、すごくない？なんか、みんなさ。
Wait, isn't this amazing? Like, everyone.
今日さ、キャンプファイヤーの前でウクレレを弾くっていう。
Today, playing the ukulele in front of a campfire.
こんな素朴な放送のために3Dやらせてもらったんだや。
I was allowed to use 3D for such a simple broadcast.
だや？（笑） すみません、どうもありがとうございます。
Daya? (laughs) Sorry, thank you very much.
すみません、お借りしております。
Sorry, I'm borrowing the studio.
平日なら、とお借りしております。はい。
I was told I could use it since it's a weekday. Yes.
では、白日、もう一回行きたいと思います。
Now, I'd like to try 'Hakujitsu' one more time.
ちょっと緊張するな、テストだからね。行きます。
I'm a bit nervous since it's a test. Here I go.
時には誰かを知らず知らずのうちに
Sometimes, without even realizing it,
傷つけてしまったり
I end up hurting someone...
失ったりして初めて犯した罪を知る
...and only through loss do I realize the sins I've committed.
戻れないよ、昔のようには
I can't go back to the way things were.
煌めいて見えたとしても
Even if it seemed to sparkle,
明日へと歩き出さなきゃ
I have to start walking toward tomorrow,
雪が降り頻ろうとも
even if the snow keeps falling heavily.
今の僕には何ができるの？
What can I do now?
何になれるの？
What can I become?
誰かのために
For someone else's sake,
生きるなら 正しいことばかり言ってらんないよな
if I'm to live, I can't just say the right things.
どこかの街でまた出会えたら
If we meet again in some town,
僕の名前を覚えていますか？
will you remember my name?
その頃にはきっと
By that time, surely,
春風が吹くだろう
the spring breeze will be blowing.
真っ新に生まれ変わって 人生一から始めようが
Even if I'm reborn anew and start life from scratch,
へばりついて離れない 地続きの今を歩いてるんだ
I'm walking through the continuous 'now' that's stuck and won't leave.
真っ白に全てさよなら 降りしきる雪よ
Goodbye to everything in pure white, oh falling snow,
全てを包み込んでくれ
please envelope everything.
今日だけは全てを隠してくれ
For today at least, hide everything away.
ちょっとだけ間違えました。どうですか、試験官のみなさん。
I made a little mistake. How was that, judges?
これがうちが練習した。
This is what I've practiced.
えっとね、この白日の最初のところは
So, the beginning part of 'Hakujitsu'...
ちょっぴり、あの…工夫して弾くことにしたんだよ。
I decided to add a bit of a personal touch to the playing.
時には〜 誰かの〜
Sometimes~ anyone~
傷つけて〜しま〜ったり
Hurt~ing~ them...
「チャッ」失い… あ、失い、そう。
'Cha!' Los...ing... Ah, losing, right.
「チャッ」が必要だということが分かったの。
I realized that a 'cha' (muted strum) was necessary.
全部同じテンポで弾くんじゃなくて
Rather than playing everything at the same tempo,
「チャッ、失ったり」って弾く場所を変えることで
by changing the rhythm to 'cha, losing', I tried to...
ちょっとメリハリが出るように工夫したりして。
...make it more dynamic with some variation.
...なんですけど、どうでしょうか皆さん？
...but how about it, everyone?
合格、あ、試験官の皆さん。いつもいつもお世話になっております。
A passing grade? Oh, examiners. Thank you for your continued support.
合格、あ、ありがとうございます。
A pass? Oh, thank you very much.
あ、ちょっと、じゃあ、ちょっとそこのこだわりの部分だけ弾かせてもらおう。
Ah, wait, let me play just that part I'm picky about.
時には誰かを 知らず知らずの うちに傷つけてしまったり
Sometimes I unknowingly hurt someone...
失ったりして 初めて犯した
Only by losing them...
罪を知る
...do I realize the sin I committed.
戻れない...
I can't go back...
ここ、これ、これです。
This, this is it.
あ、ありがとう。合格だって、ありがとうございます。
Ah, thank you. You say I passed? Thank you very much.
試験官の皆さんいつもお世話になっております。
Examiners, thank you for your continued support.
というわけでじゃあ今回もね、あの試験官の皆さんに合格をいただくことができたので、
So, since I was able to get a passing grade from the examiners this time too,
じゃあ今までね、えーと引いてきた合格曲を弾いていきたいなと思います。
I'd like to play the passing songs I've played so far.
はい。頑張ってる？ありがとう。
Yes. Am I doing my best? Thank you.
じゃあちょっとね、他の曲もいきたいと思います。じゃあ一つ...何にしようかな？
Well, I'll go with some other songs. Let's see... what should I play?
練習してきたからね。
I've practiced, after all.
はい。
Yes.
えー次はですね、えースピッツさんの空も飛べるはず。これも練習曲でしたね。これを弾きたいと思います。
Next is Spitz's 'Sora mo Toberu Hazu'. This was also a practice song. I'd like to play this.
今までのね、あの練習してきた曲を順番に弾いていって、であとはうちが好きな曲を弾いたりとかしていこうかなって思ってます。
I'm planning to play the songs I've practiced so far in order, and then maybe play some songs I like.
はい。それでは、えー空も飛べるはず。
Yes. Now, 'Sora mo Toberu Hazu'.
空も飛べるはず 作詞・作曲：草野正宗
Sora mo Toberu Hazu Lyrics/Composition: Masamune Kusano
幼い微熱を 下げられないまま 神様の影を恐れて
With a slight childhood fever that hasn't cooled down, fearing the shadow of God...
隠したナイフが 似合わない僕を おどけた歌で慰めた
The hidden knife comforted me, who it didn't suit, with a playful song...
色褪せながら ひび割れながら 輝く術を求めて
While fading, while cracking, searching for a way to shine...
君と出会った奇跡が この胸にあふれてる
The miracle of meeting you overflows in my heart
きっと今は 自由に空も飛べるはず
Surely now I should be able to fly freely in the sky
夢をぬぎ捨てた涙が 海原へ流れたら
If the tears that shed their dreams flow into the sea
ずっとそばで笑っていてほしい
I want you to be laughing by my side forever
空も飛べるはず、スピッツさんの曲でした。ありがとうございました。
'Sora mo Toberu Hazu', a song by Spitz. Thank you very much.
この曲は確か、えー試験官の皆が最初のほうに、さんぽの次だったかな？
This song was, if I recall correctly, what the examiners suggested early on, maybe after 'Sampo'?
空も飛べるはず、弾き語りでおすすめだよって言われて、あーいいかもしれないと思って、それで選びました。
They told me 'Sora mo Toberu Hazu' is recommended for singing while playing, so I thought 'Ah, that might be good' and chose it.
パチパチありがとう。
Clap clap, thank you.
思い出の曲だね。次の曲行こうかな。
It's a memorable song. Shall I move on to the next song?
次の曲はじゃあな、これにしようかな。
Next song will be... let's see, this one.
これはちょっと最近の課題曲なんだけど、
This is a song I've been working on recently,
こないだの『白日』の前だね。月光。
just before "Hakujitsu". Moonlight.
このね、『月光』の鬼束ちひろさんの曲もね、
This song, "Moonlight" by Chihiro Onitsuka,
ちょっと好きな曲なので、弾いていこうと思います。
is one of my favorites, so I'll give it a try.
ちょっと強火？（笑）
Is the fire a bit too strong? (laughs)
うちのこと炙ろうとしてるのかな？
Is it trying to roast me?
それともウクレレのこと炙ろうとしているのか。
Or is it trying to roast the ukulele?
いや大丈夫大丈夫。木で囲ってあるし多分キャンプファイヤーってこんなもんだろう。
No, it's okay. It's surrounded by logs, so I guess this is what a campfire is like.
それでは、えー、鬼束ちひろさんの『月光』。
Well then, Chihiro Onitsuka's "Moonlight".
いきます。
Here we go.
月光
作詞・作曲・鬼束ちひろ
Moonlight
Lyrics & Composition: Chihiro Onitsuka
I am GOD'S CHILD この腐敗した世界に堕とされた
I am GOD'S CHILD, falling into this rotten world
ちょっと間違えた。
Wait, I made a mistake.
ちょっと…曲が入るところから、すみません、もう一回。
One more time from the start of the song. Sorry.
I am GOD'S CHILD この腐敗した世界に堕とされた
I am GOD'S CHILD, falling into this rotten world
How do I live on such a field? こんなもののために生まれたんじゃない
How do I live on such a field? I wasn't born for something like this
突風に埋もれる足取り
Footsteps buried in sudden gusts of wind
倒れそうになるのを
Trying not to fall
この鎖が許さない
This chain won't allow it
心開けば渡しだたままで
If I open my heart, it stays handed over
あなたの感覚だけが散らばって
Only your sensations are scattered
私はまだ上手に片付けられずに
And I still can't tidy them up well
I am GOD'S CHILD 哀しい音は背中に爪跡を付けて
I am GOD'S CHILD, sad sounds leave claw marks on my back
I can't hang out this world こんな思いじゃどこにも居場所なんてない
I can't hang out this world, with these feelings I have no place anywhere
不愉快に冷たい壁とか
Unpleasantly cold walls and such
次はどれに弱さを許す?
What weakness will be forgiven next?
終わりになど手を伸ばさないで
Don't reach out for the end
あなたなら救い出して 私を
If it's you, rescue me
静寂から
From the silence
時間は痛み加速させていく
Time accelerates the pain
I am GOD'S CHILD この腐敗した世界に堕とされた
I am GOD'S CHILD, falling into this rotten world
How do I live on such a field? こんなもののために生まれたんじゃない
How do I live on such a field? I wasn't born for something like this
I am GOD'S CHILD...
おっと音が。ウクレレくんの音が。
Wait, the sound... the sound of my ukulele...
すみません。ありがとうございます。
Sorry. Thank you very much.
ちょっとね、いつもとは違う環境だからね。
It's because the environment is different than usual.
なぜかウクレレくんがどんどんツルツルツルツル左に動くんだよね。
For some reason, the ukulele keeps sliding further and further to the left.
どうしたの？ウクレレくんも緊張してるのか。
What's wrong? Is the ukulele nervous too?
落ち着いて、大丈夫？
Calm down, okay?
よしよし。どうしたどうした。
There, there. What happened?
どんどん左に行ってる、緊張してるの？
It's going left more and more, are you nervous?
緊張してるんだって。だからどんどん左に行きたくなっちゃう。
It says it's nervous! That's why it wants to keep going left.
そうです。
That's right.
どんどん勝手にズレられるとさ、どんどん弾く場所がズレてくんだよ。
If it keeps shifting on its own, where I play also keeps shifting.
はい、というわけで、えー、月光、鬼束ちひろさんの曲でした。ありがとうございました。
So, that was "Gekkou" by Chihiro Onitsuka. Thank you very much.
他にもね、課題曲いくつかありましたよね。
There were a few other assigned songs, weren't there?
次の曲は、えっと...
The next song is, let's see...
こっちかな。
Maybe this one?
あ、これかな。えっと...
Ah, this one. Um...
夜空ノムコウにしようかな。ありましたよね、夜空ノムコウもね。
I think I'll do "Yozora no Mukou". We had that one too, "Yozora no Mukou".
皆さん覚えてますか？
Do you all remember it?
ウクレレくん、リラックスして。そうだよ。
Ukulele-kun, relax. That's right.
ウクレレくん、みんなもリラックスしてって言ってるよ。頑張って。
Ukulele-kun, everyone's saying to relax. Do your best.
うん、うん。うん、うん、うん、あ...
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah, ah...
ウクレレくんもなるべく頑張るんだけど、初めてこう、ちゃんとした姿でみんなの前に出るのが恐ろしく緊張してるんだって。
Ukulele-kun says he'll try his best, but he's incredibly nervous to appear before everyone like this for the first time.
みんな、ウクレレくんのことも応援してやってね。
Everyone, please support Ukulele-kun too.
では、えー、夜空ノムコウ弾きたいと思います。はい。
Well then, I'd like to play "Yozora no Mukou". Yes.
あれから僕たちは 何かを信じてこれたかな
Since then, have we been able to believe in something?
夜空ノムコウ
作詞：スガ シカオ / 作曲：川村 結花
Yozora no Mukou
Lyrics: Shikao Suga / Composition: Yuuka Kawamura
夜空のむこうには 明日がもう待っている
Beyond the night sky, tomorrow is already waiting.
誰かの声に気づき 僕らは身をひそめた
Noticing someone's voice, we hid ourselves.
公園のフェンス越しに 夜の風が吹いた
Across the park fence, the night wind blew.
君が何か伝えようと 握り返したその手は
As you tried to convey something, the hand you squeezed back...
僕の心のやわらかい場所を 今でもまだしめつける
...still squeezes the soft spot in my heart even now.
あれから僕たちは 何かを信じてこれたかな
Since then, have we been able to believe in something?
窓をそっと開けてみる 冬の風の匂いがした
I quietly open the window; it smelled of the winter wind.
悲しみっていつかは 消えてしまうものなのかな
Is sadness something that will disappear someday?
ため息は少しだけ 白く残ってすぐ消えた
My sigh stayed white for just a moment, then quickly vanished.
あれから僕たちは 何かを信じてこれたかな
Since then, have we been able to believe in something?
夜空のむこうには もう明日が待っている
Beyond the night sky, tomorrow is already waiting.
夜空ノムコウでした。
That was "Yozora no Mukou".
あ、メンバーシップいっぱい入ってくれてありがとうございます。
Oh, thank you for all the membership joins.
はい、えー、この曲もね、確かそう、夜空ノムコウも結構、ま真ん中ぐらいに弾いた曲だったかな？
Yes, this song... I think I played "Yozora no Mukou" around the middle of my practice?
えっと、E7。E7のこのね、E7がね...
Um, E7. This E7 chord, you see...
これですね。
It's this one.
これがちょっと難しくて。E7むずい。
This one is a bit difficult. E7 is hard.
...けど練習になるからこの曲にしようと思って、E7がいっぱい出てくる。
...but I thought this song would be good practice, and it has a lot of E7 chords.
この曲を弾いたことにより、うちはE7を克服しましたね。
By playing this song, I've mastered the E7 chord.
あ、メンバーシップありがとうね。はい。
Oh, thank you for the membership! Yes.
じゃ、お次の曲いきたいと思います。えーっと、次は、ウクレレ曲の代表曲といっても過言ではない、
Now, I'd like to move on to the next song. Um, next is a song that's no exaggeration to call a representative ukulele track,
『風になる』。
"Kaze ni Naru" (Become the Wind).
あ、ウクレレくん。ウクレレくんいなくならないで。よしよし。いい子だね。はい。
Ah, Ukulele-kun. Ukulele-kun, don't disappear on me. There, there. Good boy. Yes.
あ、E7克服曲で。えー、『風になる』はすごく、あ、ウクレレ、ウクレレ、頼むよ。
Ah, the E7 mastery song. Um, "Kaze ni Naru" is really... Ah, ukulele, ukulele, I'm counting on you.
ちょっと緊張してるかもしれないけど、頼むよ。もう、自らね、そんな薪になりにいかないでくださいよ。はい。
You might be a little nervous, but please hang in there. Don't go trying to turn yourself into firewood! Okay.
『風になる』を弾きたいと思います。つじあやのさんの曲です。
I'm going to play "Kaze ni Naru". It's a song by Tsuji Ayano.
この曲はね、元々ウクレレの曲なのでね、すごい元気で歌えるということで選びました。
This song was originally written for the ukulele, and I chose it because it's such a cheerful song to sing.
リズムもちょっと、今までの『ジャンジャンジャン』とはまたちょっと違うんですよね。はい。
The rhythm is also a bit different from the 'strum-strum-strum' we've had so far. Yes.
では、つじあやのさんの『風になる』です。
So, here is "Kaze ni Naru" by Tsuji Ayano.
忘れていた目を閉じて
Close your eyes that had forgotten
風になる
作詞・作曲：つじあやの
Kaze ni Naru
Lyrics & Composition: Tsuji Ayano
取り戻せ恋のうた
And take back the song of love
青空に隠れている
Hiding in the blue sky
手を伸ばしてもう一度
Reach out your hand once more
忘れないですぐそばに
Don't forget, right by your side
僕がいるいつの日も
I am here, any and every day
星空を眺めている
Gazing up at the starry sky
一人きりの夜明けも
Even at the dawn spent all alone
たったひとつの心
With your one and only heart
悲しみに暮れないで
Don't be lost in sadness
君のためいきなんて
A sigh from you
春風に変えてやる
I'll turn into a spring breeze
陽のあたる坂道を
Up the sun-drenched hill road
自転車で駆けのぼる
I'll climb up on my bicycle
君となくした思い出のせて行くよ
Carrying the memories I lost with you
ラララララ口ずさむ
La la la la la, humming along
唇を染めていく
Staining my lips
君と見つけたしあわせ花のように
The happiness I found with you, like a flower
君と出会えたしあわせ祈るように
The happiness of meeting you, like a prayer
え、『風になる』、つじあやのさんの曲でした。
That was "Kaze ni Naru" by Tsuji Ayano.
こう、軽快なね、チャンチャチャンチャっていうのがね、あ、すごい良い感じの曲ですね。ありがとうございます。
That lighthearted 'strum-strum-strum' feel... it's a really nice song. Thank you very much.
じゃ次は、えーっと。でも、大体ね、これで終わりかな？もう他にないよね？
Next up is... wait, is this mostly it? There aren't any others, right?
これで、もう課題曲全部やったよね？いや、だいぶ上手になったね。
We've done all the assigned songs now, haven't we? Man, I've gotten quite a bit better.
一ヶ月で、これだけ弾けるようになりました。嬉しい。
After one month, I'm now able to play this much. I'm happy.
じゃ次からは、えーっと、うちが個人的に普通に好きな曲を弾いていきたい。
So, from here on out, I'd like to play songs that I personally enjoy.
じゃちょっとジブリシリーズで行こうかな。よいしょ。いや本当にな。
Maybe I'll go with a Ghibli series next. There we go. But seriously though...
や、うちさ、全然さ楽器弾けなくてさ。なんか弾き語りやってみたいなって思って、
You know, I couldn't play instruments at all. I thought I'd like to try singing and playing,
ウクレレを始めてみたんだけど。ウクレレって結構ね、あの気軽に弾けるので、
so I started the ukulele. The ukulele is actually quite easy to pick up and play,
みんなもね、え、なんか難しそうだなって思う人もね、練習して... あ、ウクレレくんがちょっと...
so if anyone thinks it looks difficult, you should try practicing... Oh, Ukulele-kun is...
たまにいなくなるけど。ウクレレくん、頑張って、もうちょっと頑張って。頼むで。はい。
...disappearing sometimes. Hang in there, Ukulele-kun. Just a little more. I'm counting on you. Okay.
ウクレレくんも、緊張はだいぶ解けてきたみたいなんですけど、ちょっぴり集中力が切れてるみたいですね。はい。
It seems Ukulele-kun has relaxed quite a bit, but maybe he's losing focus a little. Yes.
では、えー次はですね。え、ジブリの曲ちょっと続きまして、『いつも何度でも』。
Now then, for the next one. Continuing with the Ghibli theme, it's "Itsumo Nando Demo" (Always With Me).
木村弓さんが歌ってるやつですね。はい、あの、『千と千尋の神隠し』の主題歌です。
It's the one sung by Yumi Kimura. Yes, it's the theme song for "Spirited Away."
あ、メンバーシップありがとう。それでは、いきたいと思います。はい。
Oh, thank you for the membership! All right, let's get started. Yes.
いつも何度でも
作詞：覚和歌子/作曲：木村弓
Itsumo Nando Demo (Always With Me)
Lyrics: Wakako Kaku / Composition: Yumi Kimura
いつも何度でも
作詞：覚和歌子/作曲：木村弓
Always With Me
Lyrics: Wakako Kaku / Composition: Yumi Kimura
呼んでいる...
Calling out...
夢をみたい
I want to dream
悲しみは数えきれないけれど
Though sorrows are countless
その向こうできっとあなたに会える
Beyond them, I know I'll meet you
繰り返す過ちのそのたび
Every time mistakes are repeated
人はただ青い空の青さを知る
People simply learn the blueness of the blue sky
果てしなく道は続いて見えるけれど
Though the road seems to go on forever
この両手は光を抱ける
These hands can embrace the light
さよならの時の静かな胸
A quiet heart at the moment of farewell
ゼロになるからだが耳をすませる
The body, becoming zero, listens closely
生きている不思議 死んでゆく不思議
The wonder of living, the wonder of dying
花も風も街もみんな同じ
The flowers, the wind, the town—they're all the same
ラララ...
La la la...
「いつも何度でも」でした。
That was 'Always With Me'.
ちょっぴ間違えちゃったけど。ふふっ
I made a few mistakes, though. (Chuckles)
でもすごい良い曲ですね。
But it's such a great song, isn't it?
はい。じゃお次は...
Okay. Next is...
次の曲、えー、またジブリシリーズで。
The next song, uh, is another Ghibli one.
「ひこうき雲」いきたいと思います。
I'd like to perform 'Hikoukigumo'.
これは「風立ちぬ」のテーマ曲ですね。
This is the theme song for 'The Wind Rises'.
スパチャありがとう。大丈夫みんな？
Thanks for the Super Chats. Are you guys doing okay?
なんかね、あのね、ツルツル... なんか今日のウクレレ君ツルツルする。
You know, um, it's slippery... the ukulele is feeling slippery today.
どんどん左に行ってしまうからね...
It keeps sliding off to the left...
楽譜だけ見てるとね、ウクレレの位置が分からなくなってくる。あはは！
When I only look at the sheet music, I lose track of where the ukulele is. Hahaha!
ウクレレ君今日どうしてツルツルなの？
Mr. Ukulele, why are you so slippery today?
うんうんうん... あ、そういうこと？ あ、なるほど。
Mm-hmm... Oh, is that so? Oh, I see.
そっか。あのね、ウクレレ君今日みんなに初めてこうやって姿を見られるから...
I get it. You see, because it's the first time everyone is seeing him like this today...
体がツルツルになるぐらいお風呂入ってきたんだって。
...he took a bath until his body was all smooth and shiny.
しょうがないねそれならね。ツルツルになるわけだそりゃ。
Well, can't be helped then. No wonder he's so slippery.
はい。じゃお次いきたいと思います。
Alright. Let's move on to the next one.
荒井由実さんの「ひこうき雲」。
'Hikoukigumo' by Yumi Arai.
ひこうき雲
作詞・作曲：荒井由実
Hikoukigumo
Lyrics & Composition: Yumi Arai
白い坂道が 空まで続いていた
A white uphill road led all the way to the sky
ゆらゆら かげろうが あの子を包む
A shimmering heat haze envelops that child
誰も気づかず ただひとり
Unnoticed by anyone, all alone
あの子は 昇ってゆく
That child ascends
何もおそれない
Fearing nothing
そして 舞いあがる
And then, soaring up
空に あこがれて 空をかけてゆく
Yearning for the sky, racing through the sky
あの子の 命は ひこうき雲
That child's life is a vapor trail
空に あこがれて 空をかけ...
Yearning for the sky, racing through the sky...
ずっと　あのこの
Always, that child's...
いのちは...
...life...
...ひこうきぐも
...is a vapor trail.
ありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
なんか...
Something is...
どうした？ちょっと、上手くならなくなってきたな。
What's wrong? I'm starting to not play as well.
もうちょっと疲れちゃったのかな。早いな。
Maybe I've gotten a little tired already. That's quick.
いつもはね、大体1時間半から2時間ぐらい
Usually, I'm totally fine even after playing
弾いててもなんかケロッとしてるんだけど、やっぱりお外で弾くとちょっぴりね、あの、なんか、あれなのかな。
for about an hour and a half to two hours, but I guess playing outdoors is a little, you know, maybe that's why.
あ、パチパチありがとう。
Oh, thank you for the applause.
なんか、え？何？言いたいことあるって？
What? Huh? You have something to say?
あ、そう。
Oh, I see.
うん、うん、うん…あ、なるほど。うん、うん、うん。
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm... Ah, I see. Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
あ、そうなんだ。ごめんね、そんな気遣いできなくてね。
Oh, is that so. Sorry I didn't notice.
花粉症なんだって。だからお外だとちょっとね、あの、音がね、かすれちゃうみたい。
It has hay fever, apparently. So when we're outside, its sound gets a bit raspy.
しょうがないね、それは。今花粉いっぱい飛んでるみたいだからさ。
It can't be helped. It seems like there's a lot of pollen flying around right now.
それはしょうがないよね。今花粉症の人大変だよね。
That can't be helped. People with hay fever are having a hard time now.
私は花粉症じゃないからちょっと分かりにくいんだけど、ウクレレくんちょっと花粉症なんだって。
I don't have hay fever, so it's a bit hard for me to relate, but Ukulele-kun says he has hay fever.
で、いつもは家にいるから大丈夫なんだけど。空気清浄機も焚いてるしね。
He's usually fine since he's at home. With the air purifier running too.
しょうがないね、それなら。ちょっとかすれちゃうんだって。ちょっとすみませんね、皆さんね。
Well, that explains it. He says his sound gets a bit raspy. Sorry about that, everyone.
今度は森でやらないように気をつけてあげないといけないかもね。
I might have to be careful not to hold concerts in the forest next time.
ごめんね、そんな花粉の中来てくれてありがとうね。
Sorry, and thanks for coming out despite all the pollen.
じゃあ次行こうかな。
Well, shall we move on to the next one?
えっと、次はですね…あ、じゃあこれにしようかな。
Um, next is... Oh, let's go with this one.
はい。
Okay.
お次は、スピッツさんの「ロビンソン」を弾きたいと思います。
Next, I'd like to play "Robinson" by Spitz.
頑張れ。
Do your best.
はい。
Yes.
花粉症に森はきつい。そりゃそうだ。
"Forests are tough for hay fever." That's for sure.
あ、たまにいなくなっちゃう。
Oh, it disappears sometimes.
はい。頑張ってくれてますよ、ウクレレくんもね。
Yes. Ukulele-kun is doing his best too.
それでは、聞いてください。スピッツさんの「ロビンソン」弾きたいと思います。
So please listen. "Robinson" by Spitz.
新しい季節は　なぜか切ない日々で
New seasons are somehow lonely days
河原の道を　自転車で
On the riverside path, on my bicycle
走る君を追いかけた
I chased after you as you rode
思い出のレコードと　大げさなエピソードを
Memories on records and exaggerated episodes
疲れた肩にぶらさげて
Hanging from my tired shoulders
しかめつら　まぶしそうに
A scowl, looking dazzled
同じセリフ　同じ時
The same lines, at the same time
思わず口にするような
Almost unintentionally spoken
ありふれたこの魔法で
With this common magic
作り上げたよ
I've created it
誰も触れない　二人だけの国
A land for just the two of us where no one can touch
君の手を離さぬように
So that I won't let go of your hand
大きな力で　空に浮かべたら
With a great power, if I make it float in the sky
ルララ
Ru-ra-ra
宇宙の風に乗る
riding the winds of space
大きな力で　空に浮かべたら
With a great power, if I make it float in the sky
ルララ
Ru-ra-ra
宇宙の風に乗る
riding the winds of space
ルララ
Ru-ra-ra
宇宙の風に乗る
riding the winds of space
ロビンソンでした。
That was Robinson.
これまあまあ音出てたかな。
The sound was pretty good on that one.
あー、ウクレレくん頑張ったね。
Ah, my ukulele did its best.
じゃあ、えー、あとですね、残り2曲弾いて終わりにしたいと思います。
Now, I'd like to play the remaining two songs and then wrap things up.
パチパチありがとう！
Thank you for the applause!
じゃあ次は、えーっと... これにしようかな。
Now, next... I think I'll go with this one.
あいみょんさんの『マリーゴールド』、弾きたいと思います。
I'm going to play "Marigold" by Aimyon.
ちょっとお水飲もう。
I'll drink some water.
あっという間だった？
Did it go by fast?
あっという間だったね。
It really did, didn't it?
ふふ、ウクレレくんも、こんな森の中でね、花粉症なのに、よく頑張ってくれたよね。
Hehe, my ukulele also did its best in this forest, even with hay fever.
いや、今日は発表会なんでね、いろんな曲弾こうと思って持ってきてます。はい。
Well, since today is a recital, I brought several songs to play. Yes.
では、『マリーゴールド』、行きたいと思います。
So, I'm going to play "Marigold".
風の強さがちょっと
The wind's strength is a little
心を揺さぶりすぎて
Shaking my heart too much
マリーゴールド 作詞・作曲：あいみょん
Marigold - Lyrics/Composition: Aimyon
真面目に見つめた君が恋しい
I miss you, who stared at me so seriously
でんぐり返しの日々
Days of tumbling around
可哀想なふりをして
Pretending to be pitiable
だらけてみたけど希望の光は
I tried being lazy, but the light of hope
目の前でずっと輝いているし
Is shining right in front of me
幸せだ
I'm happy
麦わらの帽子の君が揺れたマリーゴールドに似てる
You in your straw hat look like a swaying marigold
あれは空がまだ青い夏のこと
That was a summer when the sky was still blue
懐かしいと笑えたあの日の恋
A love from that day we could laugh at as nostalgic
もう離さないでと泣きそうな目で
With eyes that looked ready to cry, saying "don't let go anymore"
見つめる君を
Gazing at you
雲のような優しさでそっとぎゅっと
With a cloud-like kindness, softly and tightly
抱きしめて 抱きしめて 離さない
Holding you, holding you, I won't let go
あぁアイラブユーの言葉じゃ足りないからとキスして
Ah, saying "I love you" isn't enough, so kiss me
雲がまた二人の影を残すから
Because the clouds will leave our shadows behind again
いつまでも いつまでも このまま
Forever and ever, just like this
離さない
I won't let go
『マリーゴールド』でした。
That was "Marigold".
ちょっとあまりミスなく弾けたので、ちょっと嬉しいです。
I was able to play it with very few mistakes, so I'm a bit happy.
ありがとう！
Thank you!
梅干しも生えてくれてる人、ありがとう！
Thank you to the person sprouting umeboshi!
パチパチありがとうございます。
Thank you for the applause.
では、最後の曲、行きたいと思います。
Now, I'd like to play the final song.
皆さんにね、あの、こんな森の中、ノスタルジックな気持ちで終わりにしたいなって思いますのでね。
In this forest setting, I'd like to end on a nostalgic note for everyone.
パチパチありがとう。本当に上手？本当に？嬉しいな。
Thanks for the applause. Am I really good? Really? I'm so happy.
では、最後の1曲は、えー、Hello, Again ～昔からある場所～
Now, the last song is "Hello, Again ~Mukashi kara aru basho~".
ま、うちがね、よくね、好きでね、歌ってる曲なんだけれども。
Well, it's a song that I really love and often sing.
この曲を歌って終わりにしようと思います。
I'm going to sing this song and finish up.
アメパチありがとうね！
Thanks for the "Amepachi"!
では、ノスタルジックな気持ちで行きます。
Here we go, with a nostalgic feeling.
My Little Lover さんの曲です。
It's a song by My Little Lover.
La la la...
Hello, Again ～昔からある場所～ 作詞：KATE/作曲：藤井謙二、小林武史
Hello, Again ~Mukashi kara aru basho~ - Lyrics: KATE / Composition: Kenji Fujii, Takeshi Kobayashi
いつも君と待ち続けた季節は
The seasons I always spent waiting with you
何も言わず通り過ぎた
Passed by without saying a word
雨はこの街に降り注ぐ
Rain pours down on this town
少しの...
A little...
に連れと罪を
...along with sins,
包み込んで
...and wrap them up.
泣かないことを
While still having
誓ったまま...
vowed not to cry...
時は過ぎ
Time passed,
痛む心に
without noticing
気が付かずに
my aching heart...
僕は一人になった
I was left alone
記憶の中で
within my memories...
ずっと二人は
The two of us
生きて行ける
can live on forever.
君の声が
Your voice...
今も胸に響くよ
...still resonates in my chest.
それは愛が彷徨う影
That is the shadow of wandering love.
君は少し泣いた
You cried a little.
あの時 見えなかった
I couldn't see it back then.
Hello, again a-feeling heart
Hello, again my old dear place
Hello, Again ～昔からある場所～
Hello, Again ~A Place That's Been There Since Long Ago~
My Little Loverさんの曲でした。ありがとうございました。
That was a song by My Little Lover. Thank you very much.
いやー、というわけで、えー以上、
Well then, that's all,
まあ計10曲ぐらいかな？弾き切ったと思うんですけれども、
about 10 songs in total, right? I think I've managed to play through them all.
うちがねウクレレを挑戦し続けて、もはや1ヶ月ちょっとですね。
I've been practicing the ukulele for a little over a month now.
ようやくここまでたどり着けましたが、
I've finally made it this far,
もっともっと上手くなりたいと思いますので、
but I want to get better and better,
これからもウクレレを弾く放送は続けていきたいなと思っています。はい。
so I'd like to continue doing broadcasts where I play the ukulele. Yes.
どうもありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
ちょっとこの後に、あのねもっと弾きたいんだけど、
I actually want to play more, but...
えー実は、この後に放送があって、
The truth is, there's another broadcast after this,
あのスモークの放送があって、
a SMOK broadcast.
あのスモークの4人でね、あのゲームをやるので、
The four of us in SMOK are going to play a game,
あのそれにのためにうちはちょっと帰らなければいけないということで、
so I have to head back for that,
あのね、こんな森の中まで来たんですけどね。
even though I've come all the way out here into the forest.
それにしてもこの森のロケーションすごいですね。
Still, this forest location is amazing.
なんか本当に何だろう、
It's like, what is this...
こんなとこあったっけ？
Was there a place like this?
なんか、初めてですよね。あれ？
It's my first time here, right? Huh?
何これ？え、何これ？何この仕切り？え？
What's this? Eh, what's this? What's with this partition? Eh?
何？駐車場？え？
What? A parking lot? Eh?
海じゃん。
It's the ocean.
ウクレレ始めて1ヶ月ちょっと...
About a month after starting the ukulele...
3D ウクレレ発表会
3D Ukulele Recital